You know what I learned from it? I learned that it is really shameful to talk about it. I learned to be ashamed of my body. I learned to stay unaware of periods in order to stay decent. Research in various parts of India shows that three out of every 10 girls are not aware of menstruation at the time of their first periods. And in some parts of Rajasthan this number is as high as nine out of 10 girls being unaware of it. You'd be surprised to know that most of the girls that I have spoken to, who did not know about periods at the time of their first menstruation thought that they have got blood cancer and they're going to die soon. Menstrual hygiene is a very important risk factor for reproductive tract infections. But in India, only 12 percent of girls and women have access to hygienic ways of managing their periods. If you do the math, 88 percent of girls and women use unhygienic ways to manage their periods. I was one of them. I grew up in a small town called Garhwa, in Jharkhand, where even buying a sanitary napkin is considered shameful. So when I started getting my periods, I began with using rags. After every use I would wash and reuse them. But to store them, I would hide and keep it in a dark, damp place so that nobody finds out that I'm menstruating. Due to repeated washing the rags would become coarse, and I would often get rashes and infections using them. I wore these already for five years until I moved out of that town. Another issue that periods brought in my life those of the social restrictions that are imposed upon our girls and women when they're on their periods. I think you all must be aware of it,
¿Saben qué aprendí de esto? Aprendí que es realmente una vergüenza hablar de ello. Aprendí a avergonzarme de mi cuerpo. Aprendí a ignorar los períodos con el fin de mantenerme decente. La investigación en diversas partes de la India muestra que 3 de cada 10 mujeres no son conscientes de la menstruación cuando tienen sus primeros períodos. Y en algunas partes de Rajasthan este número es tan alto como 9 de cada 10 niñas no son conscientes de ello. Les sorprendería saber que la mayoría de las niñas con las que he hablado que no sabían nada sobre el período en el momento de su primera menstruación pensaron que tenían cáncer de la sangre y que iban a morir pronto. La higiene menstrual es un factor de riesgo muy importante para infecciones del tracto reproductivo. Pero en la India solo el 12 % de las niñas y mujeres tienen acceso a formas de higiene para sobrellevar sus períodos. Si se hacen las cuentas, 88 % de niñas y mujeres utilizan formas poco higiénicas durante sus períodos. Yo era una de ellas. Crecí en una pequeña ciudad llamada Garhwa, en Jharkhand, donde incluso comprar una compresa higiénica se considera una vergüenza. Así que cuando comenzaron mis períodos, empecé a usar trapos. Después de cada uso los lavaba y volvía a utilizarlos. Pero para guardarlos, me escondía y los mantenía en un lugar oscuro y húmedo para que nadie se entera de que estaba menstruando. Debido al lavado repetido se volvían ásperos, y muchas veces tenía erupciones e infecciones por usarlos. Llevaba cerca de 5 años así hasta que me fui de esa ciudad. Otra de las cosas que los períodos trajeron a mi vida fueron las restricciones sociales que se imponen a nuestras niñas y mujeres cuando están en sus días. Creo que todos deben ser conscientes de ello,
but I'll still list it for the few who don't. I was not allowed to touch or eat pickles. I was not allowed to sit on the sofa or some other family member's bed. I had to wash my bed sheet after every period, even if it was not stained. I was considered impure
pero aun así las enumeraré para los pocos que no lo son. No se me permitía tocar o comer pepinillos. No se me permitía sentarme en el sofá o la cama de otro miembro de la familia. Tenía que lavar mi sábana después de cada periodo, incluso si no estaba manchada. Me consideraban impura
and forbidden from worshipping or touching any object of religious importance. You'll find signposts outside temples denying the entry of menstruating girls and women. Ironically, most of the time it is the older woman who imposes such restrictions on younger girls in a family. After all, they have grown up accepting such restrictions as norms. And in the absence of any intervention, it is the myth and misconception that propagate from generation to generation. During my years of work in this field, I have even come across stories where girls have to eat and wash their dishes separately. They're not allowed to take baths during periods, and in some households they are even secluded from other family members. About 85 percent of girls and women in India would follow one or more restrictive customs on their periods every month. Can you imagine what this does to the self-esteem and self-confidence of a young girl? The psychological trauma that this inflicts, affecting her personality, her academic performance and every single aspect of growing up during her early formative years? I religiously followed all these restrictive customs for 13 years, until a discussion with my partner, Tuhin, changed my perception about menstruation forever. In 2009, Tuhin and I were pursuing our postgraduation in design. We fell in love with each other and I was at ease discussing periods with him. Tuhin knew little about periods. (Laughter) He was astonished to know that girls get painful cramps and we bleed every month. (Laughter)
y se me prohibía adorar o tocar cualquier objeto de importancia religiosa. Encontraba avisos fuera de los templos que negaban la entrada a niñas y mujeres con el periodo Irónicamente, la mayor parte de las veces es la mujer mayor la que ha impuesto restricciones a las niñas más jóvenes de la familia. Después de todo, ellas han crecido aceptando tales restricciones como normas. Y en ausencia de cualquier intervención, el mito y la idea errónea se propagan de generación en generación. Durante mis años de trabajo en este campo, incluso he visto historias de niñas que tienen que comer y lavar sus platos por separado. No se les permite bañarse teniendo el período, y en algunos hogares incluso están aisladas de otros miembros de la familia. Alrededor del 85 % de las niñas y mujeres en la India seguirán una o más costumbres restrictivas durante sus períodos. ¿Pueden imaginar lo que esto causa en la autoestima y la autoconfianza de una niña? ¿El trauma psicológico que esto inflige, que afecta a su personalidad, su rendimiento académico y cada aspecto del proceso de crecimiento durante sus primeros años de formación? He seguido religiosamente todas estas costumbres restrictivas por 13 años, hasta que una discusión con mi pareja, Tuhin, cambió para siempre mi percepción de la menstruación. En 2009 Tuhin y me estábamos tras nuestro posgrado en diseño. Nos enamoramos y yo estaba a gusto discutiendo sobre el período con él. Tuhin sabía poco acerca de la menstruación. (Risas) Se sorprendió al saber que las chicas tienen calambres dolorosos y sangrados cada mes. (Risas)
Yeah. He was completely shocked to know about the restrictions that are imposed upon menstruating girls and women by their own families and their society. In order to help me with my cramps, he would go on the Internet and learn more about menstruation. When he shared his findings with me, I realized how little I knew about menstruation myself. And many of my beliefs actually turned out to be myths. That's when we wondered: if we, being so well educated, were so ill-informed about menstruation, there would be millions of girls out there who would be ill-informed, too. To study --
Sí. Estaba completamente sorprendido de saber sobre las restricciones que se imponen a las jóvenes y mujeres que menstrúan por sus propias familias y la sociedad. Con el fin de ayudarme con mis calambres, fue a Internet a aprender más acerca de la menstruación. Cuando compartió sus hallazgos conmigo, me di cuenta de lo poco que yo misma sabía de la menstruación. Y muchas de mis creencias en realidad resultaron ser mitos. Fue cuando nos preguntamos: si nosotros, siendo tan bien educados, estábamos tan mal informados sobre la menstruación, habrá millones de niñas que estarán mal informadas, también. Para estudiar...
to understand the problem better, I undertook a year-long research to study the lack of awareness about menstruation and the root cause behind it. While it is generally believed that menstrual unawareness and misconception is a rural phenomenon, during my research, I found that it is as much an urban phenomenon as well. And it exists with the educated urban class, also. While talking to many parents and teachers, I found that many of them actually wanted to educate girls about periods before they have started getting their menstrual cycle. And -- but they lacked the proper means themselves. And since it is a taboo, they feel inhibition and shameful in talking about it. Girls nowadays get their periods in classes six and seven, but our educational curriculum teaches girls about periods only in standard eight and nine. And since it is a taboo,
para comprender mejor el problema, investigué un año para estudiar la falta de conciencia sobre la menstruación y la causa fundamental detrás. Aunque generalmente se cree que el desconocimiento menstrual es un fenómeno rural, durante mi investigación, encontré que es también un fenómeno urbano. Y es que existe en la clase urbana educada, también. Mientras hablaba con muchos padres y profesores, descubrí que muchos realmente querían informar a las niñas sobre el período antes de que comenzaran a tener su ciclo menstrual. Y... pero carecían de medios adecuados ellos mismos. Y puesto que es un tabú, se inhiben y les da vergüenza hablar de ello. Las niñas hoy tienen la menstruación en las clases de sexto y séptimo, pero nuestro plan de estudios enseña a las niñas sobre el período solo en octavo o noveno. Y puesto que es un tabú,
teachers still skip the subject altogether. So school does not teach girls about periods, parents don't talk about it. Where do the girls go? Two decades ago and now -- nothing has changed. I shared these finding with Tuhin and we wondered: What if we could create something that would help girls understand about menstruation on their own -- something that would help parents and teachers talk about periods comfortably to young girls? During my research, I was collecting a lot of stories. These were stories of experiences of girls during their periods. These stories would make girls curious and interested in talking about menstruation in their close circle. That's what we wanted. We wanted something that would make the girls curious and drive them to learn about it. We wanted to use these stories to teach girls about periods. So we decided to create a comic book, where the cartoon characters would enact these stories and educate girls about menstruation in a fun and engaging way. To represent girls in their different phases of puberty, we have three characters. Pinki, who has not gotten her period yet, Jiya who gets her period during the narrative of the book and Mira who has already been getting her period. There is a fourth character, Priya Didi.
los maestros todavía se saltan el tema por completo. Así que la escuela no enseña a las niñas sobre el período, los padres no hablan de ello. ¿A dónde van las chicas? Hace dos décadas y ahora... nada ha cambiado. Compartí estos hallazgos con Tuhin y nos preguntamos: ¿Y si pudiéramos crear algo que ayudara a entender las niñas la menstruación por cuenta propia, algo que ayudara a padres y profesores a hablar del período cómodamente a las jóvenes? Durante mi investigación, recolecté un montón de historias. Fueron historias de experiencias de las niñas durante su período. Estas historias despertarían a las niñas la curiosidad y el interés de hablar de la menstruación en su círculo cercano. Eso es lo que queríamos. Queríamos algo que despertara a las niñas la curiosidad y las llevara a aprender del tema. Queríamos usar estas historias para enseñarles sobre el período. Así que decidimos crear un cómic, donde los personajes de dibujos animados promulgaran estas historias y educaran sobre la menstruación a las niñas de manera divertida y atractiva. Para representar a las niñas en sus diferentes fases de la pubertad, tenemos 3 caracteres. Pinki, que no ha tenido su período aún. Jiya que tiene el período durante el curso del relato del libro y Mira que ya tiene su período. Hay un cuarto personaje, Priya Didi.
Through her, girls come to know about the various aspects of growing up and menstrual hygiene management. While making the book, we took great care that none of the illustrations were objectionable in any way and that it is culturally sensitive. During our prototype testing, we found that the girls loved the book. They were keen on reading it and knowing more and more about periods on their own. Parents and teachers were comfortable in talking about periods to young girls using the book, and sometimes even boys were interested in reading it. (Laughter) (Applause) The comic book helped in creating an environment where menstruation ceased to be a taboo. Many of the volunteers took this prototype themselves to educate girls and take menstrual awareness workshops in five different states in India. And one of the volunteers took this prototype to educate young monks and took it to this monastery in Ladakh. We made the final version of the book, called "Menstrupedia Comic" and launched in September last year. And so far, more than 4,000 girls have been educated by using the book in India and -- (Applause) Thank you. And 10 different countries. We are constantly translating the book into different languages and collaborating with local organizations to make this book available in different countries. 15 schools in different parts of India have made this book a part of their school curriculum to teach girls about menstruation. (Applause) I am amazed to see how volunteers, individuals, parents, teachers, school principals, have come together and taken this menstrual awareness drive to their own communities, have made sure that the girls learn about periods at the right age and helped in breaking this taboo. I dream of a future where menstruation is not a curse, not a disease, but a welcoming change in a girl's life. And I would -- (Applause) And I would like to end this with a small request to all the parents here. Dear parents, if you would be ashamed of periods, your daughters would be, too. So please be period positive. (Laughter) Thank you. (Applause)
A través de ella, las niñas saben de los diversos aspectos del crecimiento y de como llevar la higiene menstrual. Al hacer el libro, tuvimos gran cuidado de que ninguna de las ilustraciones fueran objetables en modo alguno y que fuera sensible culturalmente. Durante la prueba del prototipo, vimos que a las chicas les encantó el libro.